Guide to the papers of Oleksii Matuk g.12
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
Oleksii Matuch Papers
Bulk, 1954-1965
1944-1965
g.12
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
0.5 Linear feet 1 box
The Oleksii Matuch Papers contain what appears to be a comprehensive collection of ephemera related to the Ukrainian-American community in Buffalo, NY during the late 1950s and early 1960s, as well as some correspondence and personal documents.
Matuch, Oleksii, 1903?-1977
Biographical/Historical note
Not much is known about Oleksii Matuch (or Matukh), other than what is contained in his death announcement in the "Svoboda" newspaper (Vol. 84, No. 214, Sept. 30, 1977): he was a resident of Buffalo, NY, was a veteran of the Ukrainian War of Independence, had been the long-time president of the "Tovarystvo Spryiannia UNRady" ("Association of Supporters of the Ukrainian National Council"), and was a parishoner at Holy Trinity Ukrainian Orthodox Church in Buffalo. He died on September 26, 1977 at the age of 74.
It appears from the contents of the collection that he took a very active interest in the activities of the Ukrainian-American community in Buffalo. By the mid 1950s, the post-WWII Ukrainian refugees had had a chance to establish themselves in their new country, and the next decade was a period of intense activity in this immigrant community.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series, as follows:
Correspondence
Personal records
Ephemera
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of fliers, programs, posters, and related ephemera for Ukrainian-American community events in Buffalo, NY, as well as church bulletins and other parish publications, and mailings and publications of Ukrainian-American organizations (most notably the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America). The collection also contains a small amount of correpondence, most notably with Bp. Platon of the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church.
Some of the event posters and other material do not indicate the year of the event (only the month and day). These have been filed at the end of the correponding folder. In addition, some posters and fliers have hand-written annotations.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for researcher use. Please contact the archivist (archives@ukrhec.org) for more information and to make arrangements.
Ob'i͡ednanni͡a demokratychnoï ukraïnsʹkoï molodi.; Plast ukraïnsʹka skavtsʹka orhanizat͡sii͡a.; Platon, Bishop of Rivne, 1891-1951; Ukrainian Congress Committee of America.; Ukrainian Youth Association of America.; Refugee camps--Germany--Northeim; Ukrainian American churches--New York--Buffalo; Ukrainian-Americans--New York--Buffalo
- Correspondence, 1944-1962; Series I.; 2 folders
  - Bishop Platon, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Association of Supporters of the UNRada, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence with and mailings from the Tovarystvo Prykhyl'nykiv Ukrains'koi Natsionnal'noi Rady.
- Personal records, 1945-1962; Series II.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Donation receipts, certificates, and membership cards.
- Ephemera, Bulk, 1954-1965; 1947-1965; Series III.; 16 folders
  - Germany, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Flier for "Ukrainian Show" at Northeim DP Camp, 1947
  - Ukrainian youth groups, 1954-1965; 3 folders
    Fliers and other ephemera for events sponsored by or involving the three major post-World War II Ukrainian-American youth groups. Most but not all of the events took place in the Buffalo area.
    - Ukrainian Youth Association of America (SUMA), 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ukrainian Scouting Organization Plast, 1954-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ukrainian Democratic Youth Association (ODUM), 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Buffalo events, 1953-1965; 4 folders
    - Ukrainian Congress Committee, 1953-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Programs and fliers for concerts, dances, protests, meetings, and other events sponsored by the UCCA.
    - Dramatychno-Muzychnyi Ansambl', 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Posters for events by the "Dramatico-Musical Ensemble" of Buffalo, including theatrical productions as well as dances and other events sposored by the Ensemble.
    - Film screenings, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Other programs, fliers and posters, 1953-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Primarily Ukrainian-American community events, events with Ukrainian-American participation or connection, or events connected to the Matuch family. Includes programs and fliers for concerts, lectures, student recitals, dances, sporting events, protests, a politial campaign rally, and other events.
  - Holy Trinity Ukrainian Orthodox Church, 1955-1965; 2 folders
    - Bulletins and other ephemera, 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Bulletins and other parish publications, including a 32-page commemorative book celebrating the parish's 5th anniversary (1950-1955). Also includes other Orthodox Church-related ephemera.
    - Meeting minutes, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Period photocopies of parish general meeting minutes.
  - St. Nicholas Ukrainian Catholic Church, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Church bulletins, reports, event programs, and other Catholic Church-related ephemera.
  - Ukrainian Congress Committee - Buffalo, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Official bulletins, reports, and other publications of the UCCA branch in Buffalo, NY.
  - Ukrainian Bandurist Chorus concerts and ephemera, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Canadian events, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Programs and ephemera related to events that took place in Canada, primarily in the vicinity of Toronto and Hamilton, Ontario.
  - Tickets and ticket stubs, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Other ephemera, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Advertising, bulletins and mailingsfrom various Ukrainian-American organizations, political publications, programs and announcements of events taking place outside of Buffalo.